{"tossups": [{"question": "Funding for this site was secured for Peter Norbeck, though it was supposed to originally be placed in the Needles region to honor Red Cloud and Lewis and Clark. After abandoning a similar commission at Stone Mountain venerating Stonewall Jackson and Robert E. Lee, Gutzon Borglum designed this monument in the Black Hills. For ten points, name this South Dakota monument featuring the faces of four presidents.", "answer": "<b> Mount Rushmore</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This group placed former king Norodom Sihanouk under house arrest after a break in their alliance. This group transformed a high school into the notorious torture center S-21. After overthrowing Lon Nol to take power, this group set the calendar to \u201cYear Zero\u201d and sought to create an agrarian society. The\u201ckilling fields\u201d were operated by, for ten points, what communist organization led by Pol Pot that ruled Cambodia in the 1970s?", "answer": "<b> Khmer Rouge</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man agreed to give up his yearly consulship as part of the Second Settlement. The Praetorian Guard was established by this ruler. This man, who gave himself the title of \u201cFirst Citizen,\u201d or \u201cprinceps,\u201dcame to power after outlasting the Second Triumvirate and winning the battle of Actium, forcing his rival Marc Antony to commit suicide. For ten points, name this first emperor of Rome.", "answer": "<b> Augustus</b> Caesar (or<b> Octavian</b>; accept Gaius Julius Caesar<b> Augustus</b>; accept Gaius <b>Octavius</b> Thurinus; prompt on Caesar; do not prompt on Julius Caesar)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A golfer from this country is the only winner of the Masters to not have his jacket stored at Augusta, after he claimed to forget to bring it back; that golfer from this country became the first non-American to win a career Grand Slam in 1968. One of the earliest non-European golf clubs was founded in this country\u2019s city of Durban. Gary Player is a golfer from this country who controversially supported Hendrik Verwoerd [feh-vert], though he later disavowed him. For ten points, name this country where the Cape Town Open is held.", "answer": "<b> South Africa</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A cartoon satirizing this meeting shows three men on the edge of a cliff and is partly titled<em> LEAP</em> <em>NO LEAP</em>. Delegates known as \u201cBlue Lights\u201d attended this meeting, which was presided over by George Cabot. A debate in Pennsylvania\u2019s senate opposed this meeting\u2019s proposal to overturn the Three-Fifths Compromise. This meeting was portrayed as treasonous by Democratic-Republicans. For ten points, name this 1815 meeting of New England Federalists.", "answer": "<b> Hartford Convention</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The leader of this organization sent a message reading \u201cWait for my call\u201d and a knife emoji to his wife shortly before she reported him missing to French authorities. Kim Jong Yang became the leader of this organization after Meng Hongwei, its first Chinese president, resigned after he was detained on bribery allegations by Chinese authorities in October 2018. For ten points, name this international agency that coordinates crimefighting efforts between nations.", "answer": "<b> Interpol</b> (or<b> International Criminal Police Organization</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "In 1887, this device was the agreed upon solution to the problem that the Gerry Commission tried to resolve. Dentist Albert Southwick was inspired to invent this object after an incident involving a drunken man. Often employed at Sing Sing, this device was used in 1953 on a couple found to have leaked nuclear program secrets to the Soviets. For ten points, name this device used to execute the Rosenbergs, that relies on sending a current through the victim\u2019s body.", "answer": "<b> electric chair</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This government renounced its claims over the Baltic States after it was forced to sign the Treaty of Rapallo. This government\u2019s parliament was torched by Marinus van der Lubbe, leading to a crackdown on civil liberties in a series of Fire Decrees. Thanks to heavy debt from the War Guilt Clause, this government faced hyperinflation of the deutschemark. For ten points, name this German republic that was established following World War I.", "answer": "<b> Weimar</b> [vye-mar] Republic", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A new religious movement from this country worships \u201cGod the Parent\u201d and teaches about achieving the \u201cJoyous Life.\u201d Along with that religion, Tenrikyo, another new religious movement in this country became recognized as a terrorist group after it released sarin gas in a subway. A controversial shrine in this country honors war criminals, and many other shrines in this country honor spirits or deities called\u201ckami.\u201d For ten points, name this East Asian country home to Shintoism.", "answer": "<b> Japan</b> (or<b> Nippon</b>; or<b> Nihon</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "After manning a machine gun during this event, Dorie Miller became the first African-American to receive a Navy Cross. A perpetrator of this event was apprehended in the Niihau incident by civilians. This event was carried out in two waves by Vals and Zeroes, who sunk the<em> Arizona</em>. President Roosevelt lamented \u201ca date that will live in infamy\u201d in a speech to Congress after, for ten points, what surprise attack that brought America into World War II?", "answer": "attack on<b> Pearl Harbor</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s son Fu Su was forced to commit suicide over his support for general Meng Tian. Under the advice of chancellor Li Si, this man implemented increasingly Legalist policies. This man burned the books of Confucian scholars and buried them alive to eliminate dissent. To prepare for the afterlife, this man adorned his tomb with thousands of terracotta warriors. For ten points, name this first emperor of a unified China.", "answer": "Qin<b> Shi Huang</b>di (accept<b> Ying</b> Zheng; accept<b> Zhao</b> Zheng; accept<b> King Zheng</b> of Qin)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A speech by this man notes \u201cFondly do we hope, fervently do we pray, that this mighty scourge of war may speedily pass away.\u201d In that speech, this man advocated for a policy of \u201cmalice toward none with charity for all.\u201d This man noted that a \u201cgovernment by the people... will not perish from this earth\u201d in a speech that began \u201cFour score and seven years ago...\u201d For ten points, name this President who delivered the Gettysburg Address.", "answer": "Abraham<b> Lincoln</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Maria Reiche\u2019s studies of these works has led her to be nicknamed \u201cthe Lady\u201d of them. Drone research has led historians to conclude that these works were inspired by similar ones created by the Paracas Culture. An Adler Planetarium astronomer claimed that these works were created for the purpose of pointing out \u201cheavenly shapes.\u201d Created roughly 2,000 years ago, these works were made by the removal of dark sand to expose lighter colored soil below. Animals like jaguars and llamas are depicted in, for ten points, what natural artworks created in ancient Peru?", "answer": "<b> Nazca Lines</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "During a siege of this city, a prisoner was freed after he held his hand in a fire without injury. During another siege, this city was betrayed by a woman who was crushed by shields before being thrown from the Tarpeian rock. Those sieges were carried out by Lars Porsenna and Titus Tatius, the latter being a king of the Sabines. The early history of this city was described in Livy\u2019s<em> Ab Urbe Condita</em>. For ten points, name this city legendarily founded by Romulus and Remus.", "answer": "<b> Rome</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A policeman complained \u201cI have just bought some new furniture\u201d when he was suspended from his job in 1963 after the revelation that he had arrested this author years earlier. This author, who called herself a \u201cbundle of contradictions,\u201d addressed her work to a character she created named \u201cKitty.\u201d For ten points, name this author who died in Bergen-Belsen concentration camp after writing a diary in hiding.", "answer": "Annelise Mary \u201cAnne\u201d<b> Frank</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "This ship\u2019s passengers became the subject of a charity fund operated by James Pennington. Shortly after Joseph Cinque seized control of this ship, it was captured off of Long Island by the<em> Washington</em>. This ship, owned by Ramon Ferrer, had been redirected from Cuba to New York, triggering an 1841 Supreme Court case that ruled that this ship\u2019s Mende captives were free. For ten points, name this Spanish ship that was taken over by a slave revolt.", "answer": "La<b> Amistad</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "An Eddie Adams photograph taken during this war shows police chief Loan holding a gun to the head of a prisoner on a public road moments before executing him. In 2016, Facebook banned posts of a photo taken during this war showing a naked girl fleeing a napalm attack. A photograph of Mary Ann Vecchio kneeling over the body of Jeffrey Miller was taken at Kent State University during, for ten points, what heavily protested 1970s war whose veterans are memorialized by a wall in Washington, D.C.?", "answer": "<b> Vietnam</b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In one work, this man called for a \u201cradical revolution of values\u201d after claiming \u201c[his] conscience leaves [him] no other choice.\u201d Another of this man\u2019s works noted how \u201cno lie can</b> <b>live forever.\u201d This orator of the \u201cHow Long, (+)</b> <b>Not Long\u201d speech claimed that a group</b> <b>has been given a \u201ccheck which has come back marked insufficient funds\u201d after predicting an\u201cinvigorating autumn of (*)</b> freedom and equality.\u201d In that speech, this man hopes his four children will be \u201cjudged not by the color of their skin but by the content of their character.\u201d For ten points, name this civil rights activist who gave the \u201cI Have a Dream\u201d speech.", "answer": "Dr. Martin Luther<b> King</b>, Jr. (accept<b> MLK</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This institution was based on the earlier</b><em><b> katorga</b></em><b> system, and its growth turned Magadan into an industrial city. This institution was praised in the report</b><em><b> Solovki</b></em><b> by Maxim Gorky.</b> <b>This system was compared to an (+)</b> <b>archipelago in an Alexander Solzhenitsyn novel that</b> <b>brought it to the public\u2019s attention. NKVD-led kangaroo (*)</b> trials led political opponents to be sent to these locations. For ten points, name this system of forced labor camps set up in Siberia under Joseph Stalin.", "answer": "<b> gulag</b> system", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man adopted the Plan of Cuernavaca and the Seven Laws, though he dissolved Congress afterwards regardless. This man was removed from power by the Plan of Ayutla after serving (+) 11 non-consecutive terms. During the Pastry War against the French, this man was struck by a cannon at (*) </b> Veracruz and had his amputated leg buried with full military honors. For ten points, name this Mexican general who failed to thwart the Texan Revolution, despite leading forces at the Alamo.", "answer": "Antonio Lopez de<b> Santa Anna</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One of these things inspired and names the second and most famous symphonic poem in Bedrich Smetana\u2019s collection</b><em><b> Ma vlast</b></em><b>, known as \u201cThe Moldau\u201d or \u201cVltava.\u201d The spacecraft</b> <b>docking scene in (+)</b> <em><b>2001: A Space Odyssey</b></em><b> was set to a piece of music named for one</b> <b>of these things. Handel\u2019s</b><em><b> Water Music</b></em><b> was commissioned to be played while King George II (*) </b> traveled along one of these features. For ten points, name this type of geographic feature that inspired Johann Strauss\u2019 waltz \u201cOn the Beautiful Blue Danube.\u201d", "answer": "<b> river</b>s (accept Danube<b> River</b> after \u201cspacecraft\u201d is read; accept Thames<b> River</b> after \u201cHandel\u201dis read)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This man seized the Stone of Destiny after his troops deposed John Balliol at the battle of Dunbar. While leading troops for his father, this man was captured at Lewes but later escaped and defeated the rebellious (+) Simon de Montfort at the Battle of Evesham. After succeeding (*)</b> Henry III as king, this man defeated the rebellion of William Wallace to become known as the \u201chammer of the Scots.\u201d For ten points, name this English king who was nicknamed for his great height.", "answer": "<b> Edward I</b> (accept<b> Edward Longshanks</b>; prompt on Edward; prompt on Longshanks)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this event which forced an Italian to recant his heliocentric claims.", "answer": "<b> trial</b> of<b> Galileo</b> Galilei (accept descriptive equivalents) ", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The exploits of these people prompted John Thach to develop a system known as</b> <b>the \u201cBig Blue Blanket.\u201d These people traditionally dropped flowers and saluted while</b> <b>passing Mount Kaimon. They first appeared at the Battle of (+)</b> <b>Leyte Gulf, but</b> <b>became so prevalent at Okinawa that the battle became known as the (*)</b> \u201ctyphoon of steel.\u201d These people commonly carried out their attacks aboard Zeroes. For ten points, give this term for World War II-era Japanese pilots who targeted their planes into Allied ships on suicide missions.", "answer": "<b> kamikaze</b> pilots (prompt on descriptive answers of Japanese pilots and/or suicide attackers; prompt on \u201cdivine wind\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}